Well, where is the line? Where How does
this actually get fixed? Do I write some
pre-prompt that says, "Hey, if Keith
tries to role-play with you, just say
no." You know, like like it And they did
that eventually, by the way.
I'm sure they did. I have no doubt that
they did.
Hey everyone, this is Technogeek here.
Just wanted to give a quick shout-out to
our latest sponsor, Project Discovery.
Now, Project Discovery makes a lot of
tools that you probably know of or have
even used. One of them is Nuclei, and
the latest release of Nuclei is version
3.2. Now, 3.2 comes with a lot of really
awesome new features.
Two that I really wanted to highlight
here for you are the authenticated
scanning and the advanced fuzzing
support. Now, for authenticated
scanning, it used to be that you would
have to do all your Nuclei scanning
against unauthenticated endpoints or
you'd have to add your cookies manually,
all that kind of messy no more. It's all
automatic. You can use existing login
templates to automatically log in to
your application, and then you can run
all your existing Nuclei templates
against an authenticated part of the
application now to really increase your
coverage. The other that I mentioned is
advanced fuzzing support. Now, Nuclei
had added way back in version 2.8 the
ability to fuzz different things, but
now they've expanded this
comprehensively across the board. So,
not only can you fuzz in the normal
spots, but you can fuzz within headers,
you can fuzz within cookies, you can
fuzz within specific parts of the body,
whether that's in JSON or XML or form
data, and so many more things. So, if
you want to learn more about what came
in Nuclei 3.2, go ahead and check out
the the release blog post over at
nux.gg/podcast.
That's nux.gg/podcast.
Thanks. Alrighty, we have another
episode of Critical Thinking here today,
and I want to start this one off with a
shout-out to my co-host Joel Margolis,
who has not abandoned us today despite
just having a tractor delivered to his
house. It took everything in my power.
Everything in my power. I'm just sitting
here thinking like about roaming around
the yard on my new tractor.
Yeah, I I can tell because that means so
many so many pictures of this tractor
and videos of this tractor. So,
shout-out to Joel. Also, shout-out to
Mr. Keith here. Keith, welcome to the
podcast, man.
Hey man, long-time listener, first-time
caller.
You know, as I think I've said to you
guys before, this is a public service
that you're doing with this podcast, so
it's a real honor to be here. Thank you.
Awesome. Thanks so much. I appreciate
you listening, and yeah, I've seen you
engaged around the community, too, so
always appreciate that as well.
Um
Keith, we our two primary topics for
this episode today are going to be AI
bias bounties and that whole experience
you had with Bugcrowd and sort of that
um
very trendsetting
program that you guys were a part of
where you were doing some AI bias
testing and getting bounties for that,
which is really cool, and a continuation
of the VDP chat because
you had some hot takes, man, after the
VDP episode that you hit me with, and I
was like, "Wait a second. I want to hear
these two fight about stuff." So, I'm
sitting here and I'm talking to Justin,
and uh Justin was like, "Joel, did you
read through this doc yet?" And I was
like, "No."
He's like
He's like, "There's uh
he he wants to talk to you about VDP
stuff." And I was like, "Oh."
And I just like pulled up and I started
reading, and I was like, "Uh-oh."
Yeah.
So, it's going to be good. It's going to
be good.
Whenever you want Whenever you want to
kick that off, we can we can set that
for Well, if we're going to go to we're
going to do the AI bias bounty things
first, but I will say just as a teaser,
there is a line in the doc that Keith
wrote that starts with
"Oh, my sweet summer child, Joel."
I'm expecting some good stuff out of the
the rest of this of this pod, but
Keith, I want to get an intro from you
first to for the people that aren't
familiar with your work, so maybe you
can give us a little bit of career
history, how you ended up where you're
at in infosec, and what your experience
is with bug bounty.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So,
I'll go all the way back, you know, it
was sort of funny when we were reading
through some of like the prep stuff. So,
my first hack was in 1997. Yeah. I was
like 12 at the time. And I was just got
a new computer, 533 MHz PC with a 288
dial-up like
Blazing fast. You know, those were the
days. Yeah, blazing fast.
And and so, Diablo had just come out,
and battle.net was a thing. Yeah, like
original OG number one Diablo. And um
the funniest part was on the back of the
like CD case for the game, they had a
like a trial code that you could go in
with a trial account. Well, I learned
that you could use Telnet and any
account that wasn't currently logged in
as a username on the trial account and
just log in. Uh so,
I did what any enterprising juvenile
delinquent in the late '90s would do,
and I basically wrote VB script to
create these bots that would connect as
many connections as my 56K dial-up could
connect. Uh it was the best when I was
losing StarCraft games later, where I
would just like spin that up and spam my
friends, so they literally could just
crash offline.
And I was like, "Yeah, win the game by
default."
Uh so, I I caused trouble back in the
late '90s, and you know, one of the
things that I say to people is the whole
reason the security industry even exists
today is because disk space got cheap.
That's it.
It wouldn't exist in the fashion that it
exists today unless you could log
everything. But back then, you couldn't
cuz disk space was expensive. So, I got
away with a lot of things. Um I believe
that. I believe that. Given that one
example, I believe that. And I was at
that in 1997 at that time, I was the
ripe age of one. And Joel, I don't Were
you even born yet? How I was born I was
born in November 1997, so when
when battle.net launched, so did I.
Yeah, and it's funny because it's like
it doesn't even exist in the same way
that it it used to. It used to be like
an mIRC chat room that like you you
basically if you were in a channel and
you were the top person in the channel,
you had the ban hammer. And so, there
was this whole scene at that time where
basically all of these different like
clans would spin up bots and try to take
over each other's channels. So, it was
funny. I was looking at like
you know, one of the producing studios
that you guys work with, their logo is
the same logo as like the badass like
the super badass hackers back then
called Illuminati, where they had like
the closed square brackets with like a
an I in the middle.
Really? Wow. Yeah, and they they had an
mIRC, which I joined on Windows 95. I
ended up getting WinNuked offline cuz
they had my IP address. Uh back before
Windows 98 even came out. And so, like
Anyway, that that's
I'm old. So, like let's fast forward
though.
Okay. All right. All right. All right.
Fast forwarding, um
went to school for psychology cuz I was
a super nerd and could hack things, but
I couldn't do people. And so, I was
like, "I got to be able to do people to
be successful in my life."
that. I like that. You can already do
the tech stuff, so you're like, "All
right, where can I fill myself out a
little bit here?"
Right, right, right. So, I graduate in
May of 2009,
which is the bottom of the stock market
after the housing market crashed.
The economy. Yeah. Right. I mean, you
know, bug bounty didn't exist, right?
That was like part of it, too. And
the funny thing is is at that time like
the number one company that was hiring
people with psychology degrees that were
technical was Facebook. Mm. Now, I never
went to work at Facebook, but like they
they've hired so many people with
psychology degrees that I'm sure
someone's going to listen to this and be
like, "Let's go hire this guy."
Or maybe not, I don't know.
Um but But anyway, so few years pass,
I'm working shitty jobs, just you know,
trying to make ends meet, helping my
wife through her master's degree, and
eventually I go back to university for a
computer science degree, which I
probably should have done in the first
place. Like that just made a lot of
sense.
And I had been following the security
scene, you know, for years at that
point, listening to podcasts like Paul
Asadoorian's stuff with Security Weekly,
Patrick Gray's stuff on Risky Business.
And um
started doing collegiate cyber defense
competitions. I was like, you know, the
old man on the team. I was a decade
older than everybody else in the team.
Nice. And yeah, it was just like
Whenever they see anything legacy,
they're like, "Keith."
Yeah, god, right? It's like, "Hey, what
is this thing? Oh."
What is Telnet?
Yeah,
yeah. We're trying to put a backdoor on
a Windows 95 box. Can you
Can you help us with that? It's like,
"Oh, yeah, I got you."
Oh my god.
you not, there was software back in
those days that you could like basically
take a GIF or a JPEG image or something
and like spin it into like a backdoor or
like a reverse connection, and then send
it to your friends on AOL Instant
Messenger. Like This is not good.
Yeah, it was it was
Again, logging was expensive.
Don't do this at home, today's kids.
You'll get You'll get in jail. Uh so,
Anyway, so I got out into industry after
meeting an alumni who started a pen
testing firm. I was brought in to be a
pen tester. Mm. Really, they wanted me
to be a Splunk architect and go and
install Splunk for a bunch of small
medium businesses and government
agencies, and I was like, "No, this
sucks."
So, eventually went to Rapid7 for a
little while, mostly focusing on
AppSpider at the time. It's now called
InsightAppSec to like support their
customers.
And
got involved with BSides Boston and as
an organizer and volunteer, and then
eventually I
was reached out to by the folks at
Bugcrowd, and they're like, "Hey, we we
see you're doing a lot of stuff, and
like you're at Rapid7, you're working on
the like AppSpider product, so you know
a bit of web app sec. Like, would you
interview for this role on trust and
security?
And I was like, "Sure."
And right around that time I learned
that my training for offensive web
hacking was accepted to DerbyCon. Now, I
don't know if you guys remember
DerbyCon, but it was one of those
doesn't exist anymore for anyone that
goes and looks for it, right? Um but I
didn't know that. That's too bad.
Yeah. Yeah, it's sad, really. But it
sold out like within minutes most years
for the conference. And so to be
accepted to train at that conference was
like, "Holy cow." And that was sort of
the year that I feel like I made it in
security because I interviewed with
Jason Haddix, who's now my good friend
and my sensei. And I told him, "I'm
training at DerbyCon." He's like, "Holy
Holy crap, you're training at DerbyCon?"
I was like, "Yeah. Is that like is that
as big of a deal as you're making it out
to be?" And like
Yeah, apparently it was. And so
eventually I joined Bugcrowd, worked for
Jason. Um and that's when I really got
into the bug bounty scene. Mostly
hacking on like
a shall not be named automotive company,
some networking gear stuff companies,
like a few other things. But when you
work on a bug bounty platform and
Joel, I think you've got some experience
there too. Like you can't
work on paid programs usually
for that platform cuz you have too much
insider info.
Um
And then I started a podcast,
Application Security Weekly with Paul
Asadoorian.
Yeah.
I I wanted to I wanted to ask about
that, man. So when Do you remember when
it was that you started that podcast?
What year was?
January of 2018. January 2018. Okay, so
not not too not too long ago. I was
going to say like if you were if you
were back in the OG days of of
podcasting, that would have been that
would have been pretty crazy as well.
But yeah, it's it's definitely an
experience and it it I I
I can tell, man. Just the way you show
up to this podcast, you definitely got
some podcaster vibes about you.
I've done it before. I mean and it's a
lot of fun too because you can have
really great debates. You can meet
really interesting and talented people
like as you have on your show all the
time, right?
It's wonderful.
And and so yeah, that's sort of like
you know, 2017 DerbyCon. That's when I
sat down and chatted with Paul
Asadoorian and we started the podcast.
one more question about the podcasting
though. Like why did you cuz you're not
actively doing it anymore, right? Why
why did you drop it?
Yeah.
I shouldn't have is maybe the first
thing that I'll say.
But part of it was because you know, in
I joined Thermo Fisher Scientific. So
background about like how that all
happened. So
at DerbyCon, I'm talking with the leader
for their like risk and governance
like vulnerability management team at
Thermo Fisher about starting a bug
bounty program. And I'm working at
Bugcrowd and convince them that they
should do that. And they do like a
two-week scoped test.
Uh I also met with Paul Asadoorian and
officially like agreed to start
Application Security Weekly there. Like
everything happened because of that
conference for me.
The bug bounty program for them did not
go as planned. It did not last two
weeks. I'll just put it that way.
The the pen test? The pen test. Yeah,
the two-week scoped test that they had
because they didn't have a proper app
sec program and they got wrecked, like
wrecked. And so
start the podcast the guy, Brian Nagaki,
good friend of mine, listens to the
podcast, giving me some feedback. And
then we just start talking about
DevSecOps and app sec and doing
security. And he's like, "You need to
come work here and like build the
program here at Thermo Fisher." And I
was like
It's a good offer. Let's talk. Yeah,
right? You know, why not? So I literally
built it from the ground up. I was
employee zero on the app sec team at
Thermo Fisher. Wow.
That's a place to be.
Right? I mean and and um
Fortune 100 company, global footprints,
like
not a bad space to really cut your teeth
and build some opinions about these
different things at scale, right?
Because
I think at the end of So to answer your
question though, the reason that I
stopped podcasting is I was getting
promoted into from manager to senior
manager about a year later, a lot more
responsibility, focusing on career. I
was putting a lot of effort into the
podcast and
it just like the return on investment
didn't make a ton of sense at that point
in time. Although
quite frankly, from a reputation and
brand standpoint, it was a good thing.
And at some point I'd like to get back
into it probably because I enjoyed
the conversations, right?
Yeah. Yeah, podcasting is a long game,
man. I I know for the first year, you
know, until we actually got some some we
got a team around us and that sort of
thing. Like Joel and I were really
really hustling with this pod. You can
tell. It was it was a lot a lot of work,
man. You know, editing all the things,
you know, running the social media,
doing this and that on the Discord,
planning the episodes, getting the
guests, coordinating I mean it's just
it's a lot. So really grateful to the
team that we have now because it makes
it a lot more We're at a point now, I
think we're over the hump. It's a little
bit more sustainable. We're in like this
rhythm where we can
can do it long-term and pay the
long-term, you know, costs or whatever.
And you still get to have the fun
conversations and and most of that stuff
is dealt with, which I really I really
appreciate. So
um And it's good for your career
long-term, too. Like you might not
always be a full-time bug bounty hunter.
Like Joel, you might decide to switch
companies that you're working for. And
like being able to point to your corpus
of work and like the knowledge that
you've gained, the things that you've
shared, like Yeah. that will forever be
valuable.
So and the connections you make, right?
Like that's also super valuable.
Absolutely. And
we've talked about it on the pod before,
but even as a full-time bug bounty
hunter, you know, people will message me
all the time with bugs and be like,
"Hey, I've got this bug and can you help
me exploit it?" And
you know
probably 80% of the time it's like, "You
know, this is kind of a meh bug. You
know, it's not really anything." But
then that other, you know, 20% of the
time whatever, it's like, "Oh, hm. You
do have something good there." And yeah,
you're just missing this, you know, and
then you get some bounties and it's
great. So it's definitely worked out for
me as well as a full-time bug bounty
hunter. And and also, you know, the
Joel, I don't know if we ever shouted
this out on the on the podcast, but we
talked a couple weeks ago about how um
Yes We Hack had some awesome swag from
the event that they ran. And like a
couple weeks later, the box shows up at
my door and it's got like full of
awesome. Dude, go go go go go get it,
man. Go get it. And it's got like a
bunch of swag in there, really high
quality stuff, too. So
Dude, that's legit.
Look check that out. Look at that. Look
at that. That's Nice. So shout out to
the Yes We Hack team. I think we already
shouted them out, but
yeah, there's definitely lots of
benefits to that. So it'd be great to
see you get back into the podcasting
space, man.
Um See, but now now I'm I'm a little bit
of a crossroads cuz I'm like, "Okay."
You're you're talking about, you know,
working at Thermo Fisher Scientific and
you're
you know, now we could just slide right
into the VDP section. So I don't know.
Talk to me a little bit because like you
you started a VDP at Thermo Fisher
Scientific. And like you said, they got
wrecked in that pen test, right? So you
don't want to just, you know, join the
team there the other day the next day
and then spin up a bug bounty program
and start handing out, you know,
thousand-dollar bounties left and right.
So you decided to go to a VDP. And I
think this is where a lot of uh the
stuff that we talked about on the pod a
couple weeks ago and and your opinion
sort of collides is like when a VDP is
appropriate and what kind of
restrictions are in place around that.
And I'll just say just from my my
position as a as a hacker and as, you
know, somebody who hasn't dealt a lot
with the corporate side, I learned a lot
from that discussion that I had with
Joel and then a lot of the conversations
that I had with people over DM
afterwards. So um definitely constantly
updating my opinion on all this. But I'm
excited to hear your take on on, you
know, one, how you did it and what the
correct flow was.
Yeah, VDPs are are one of those things
where it's like I think they have the
right place in the industry at times,
especially for hackers that want to get
into something and they're maybe just
cutting their teeth, right? And so it's
it's a nice place to go and get some
practice. But um what's interesting is
like the evolution of VDPs over time
because
sort of the the thing that I remember
getting actually really mad at Bugcrowd
about
back in 2018, 2019 was when they removed
points for VDP
because I was like no one has any
incentive now to to even like report
anything to us in the first place.
And so anyway
sort of the long story short there is
like even though it was a vulnerability
disclosure program and it didn't have
any points, we actually did pay bounties
to hackers that sort of came and
continuously gave us good stuff. So so
the thinking that we had when we put
this in place was sort of first of all,
we definitely know we have too big of a
footprint to properly secure when it
comes from like a mitigation standpoint.
Not to mention the product management
teams within the various parts of the
company. And to give you a sense of like
company structure
every business group, which is like
four to 12 divisions or something like
that is based on an area of science. And
they have thousands of employees in each
area. I mean like Thermo Fisher today is
130,000
people in the company, right? Huge. And
so yeah, I mean and and my team
Yeah, and
my team at the time was 11 people. Like
like at the very highest point of the
structure of my app sec team inside that
organization, 11 people.
Not a lot of people. So so the VDP was
set up mostly because one, we knew we
had a ton of bugs out there.
In fact, there was a an Irish hacker,
Noel Softley, who actually his I think
it was his fiance at the time, now his
wife worked in a science lab using
devices from Thermo Fisher. And so he
went and found firmware out on the
internet that we made available for our
devices, reverse engineered it and found
database like connection string
information and all this other stuff.
It's always really interesting to to
hear about these companies, by the way,
that like own an industry that you don't
really know about.
For anybody interested, if you look up
Thermo Fisher, their market cap is 225
billion dollars.
Yeah, with a B, right? It's huge.
And I didn't really know about them
either until
really until what we sold to them at
Bugcrowd and then eventually when I
joined. But to give you like background
for anyone that's like Thermo Fisher
Scientific
if you've ever taken medicine of any
kind, you've probably interfaced with a
product that touched one of their
devices. Like quite literally they do
material and structural analysis, in
vitro diagnostics,
forensics, like
they make everything from like masks,
gowns, face shields to pipettes, pipette
tips,
benchtop cycling devices to the super
cold freezers that are used to store
like COVID-19 vaccines.
Mhm.
And everything in between.
And at And at max you had 11 people on
that sec team.
Yeah. Yeah, yeah, yeah. So Noam comes in
is this is exactly what I was talking
about though, Keith. Like that is that
is like very bad, right?
Yeah, I agree.
mean,
were you just like screaming the whole
time that you were in that organization?
Like how did you deal with that?
you eat the elephant one bite at a time,
right? Like that's sort of the way that
we approached it. And so it was as much
as we could scale various things we were
trying to implement, that's sort of how
we just operate, right? And and you sort
of
accept the risk and many times it's like
I can't secure everything. So what am I
going to do? Well, secure the things
that are most important. The the things
that generate revenue for the company
top priority. Like that's just where it
is.
So so Noam found some stuff, reported it
to us. Eventually he was immigrating to
the US, we hired him on the team cuz
it's like
crack reverse engineer, yeah, we want
him on the team, right? We're going to
have some actual device security stuff
we need to do.
And so
over time though what we ended up doing
is we ended up basically saying like
look, if a if a hacker came to us with a
VDP and they're like pay me, it's like I
respect your thoughts and opinions on
this. I get it, right? I've I've I'm in
that scene, I've done some bug bounty
hunting, like I understand the desire to
get paid for your work.
But we're a VDP and we've never said
we're going to pay you. So like I
encourage you to go hack on programs
that say they will pay you for your work
because
that if that's your goal, then that's
what you should do. If you want to stay
and help us make our company more
secure, we appreciate that. We can't
guarantee promise of payment, but over
time we were able to actually say look
at all this good work these hackers are
doing. Like can I get some budget that I
can throw into this and then selectively
reward hackers for consistently
providing good work to us. Uh there was
a hacker that was from the Middle East
that I you know, we were talking about
this just before we started recording
who consistently found like high and
critical bugs against our stuff,
reported them to us, like wasn't asking
for money. And we're like we're going to
give this guy some money. And so we
started doing that. Like he'd report
some things to us and we throw him, you
know, five grand here, few grand there,
right? And eventually when he graduated
college, he sent us a photo of him in
his like graduation like robe and like
cap next to a brand new car that he
bought with the bug bounty money we paid
him, which felt so good. But we also
recognized that if we had paid for every
single bug, like we could have never
even run the program.
have sent you sent you a picture with
his fleet of Teslas.
I know, right? Right? But but you know
I get it. Like VDPs I think especially
for some of the ones that I've
interfaced with. Like one of the ones I
interfaced with really recently. I'll
give you for the pod, I think your your
audience will appreciate this. So it
it's a
it's a food product. I'll just put it
that way. So it's a or a beverage. So a
beverage company Okay.
has a bug bounty program Who could we be
talking about here? There's a lot of
them, right? There's maybe a few of
them, right?
Yeah, a lot. Continue, Keith.
There's There's a few of them. But a
beverage company has this bug bounty
program and or VDP, excuse me.
And wide open scope. Like or at least a
really wide scope. And I found that they
have a credit union website.
Great place to go hack on, right? So if
you ever see a credit union for any of
your targets, go test there cuz you're
probably going to find some good stuff.
Well, I go to register an account and lo
and behold they have just a client side
validation on the email. You have to
have at company name.com as part of your
email address. And I'm like
you know, intruder just like or
intercept like grab all the stuff and
change it.
When I go to put in the social security
number, which is just a random number
that I threw in there, it sends back a
put request that gave me the full name,
address, and like account information
for this individual who had that social
security number registered with this
company in their credit union. This is a
global corporation.
how you just threw in a random social
security number and it's like oh yeah,
Bill does actually work here.
And I'm just like that finding, I could
have literally just iterated through all
nine digits of the social security
number for everybody and got all
employee information plus their address
plus their full name plus all their
social like
VDP, all I got was a thanks. That's like
a 10K crit, maybe a 20K crit for like
the sensitivity of the things that I
could get from that account. So
Yeah, you'd hope so especially when when
a company's that big. Um so yeah, I I
think I think that kind of brings us
back into that last conversation we were
having last time about on the pod when
we were talking about VDPs
about what kind of companies should be
permitted to run a VDP. And
and I don't know. Joel
you had some hot takes on that last
time.
What do you think about this massive
company
Oh jeez, my light ring just fell.
Uh to you know, 250 billion dollar
market cap
doing a VDP and not paying for bugs like
this.
I hope their cyber insurance is good.
That was a huge focus. I'm not going to
lie, that was definitely a huge focus of
the CISO.
Because you know, the reality is that if
you're not putting a financial value on
that, right? And like it's obvious that
they have plenty of money that you know,
like
it's I I don't know, it's just um it's
kind of
uh
irresponsible in my opinion, right? Like
when when you have that much money, it
doesn't take a lot of effort to put some
focus on your security. And especially
it's like company that deals with
medical and very sensitive data, right?
Like security should be a focus and I
don't think that's something that if you
go to the shareholders and you're like
uh we're going to spend, you know, a
billion dollars on
security in the next 5 years.
Like I don't think the shareholders
could be like why, you know? Well, why?
Cuz we're a medical company and we deal
with a lot of sensitive information.
Like it doesn't really need
justification, right? Like look at all
the hacks, look at all the money that
was lost in previous data breaches of
large companies and then look at us.
Right?
So I think
you know, it's it's definitely
especially for like the larger like the
larger the company, the more difficult
it is for me to justify.
I agree. I mean like and to the extent
that I put something in here in the show
notes for us to chat about as well and
and I've given it as a talk at a few
different places, but I have this
analogy that I like to use, which is
security is a feature.
And I'm usually talking to development
teams or product teams when I'm using
that as an analogy. But let me let me
give you guys like the thing that I ask
these product teams.
you better talk, Keith cuz
I'd love
I'd love this so far. So so so so let me
ask you guys this is the exact same
question that I ask these development
teams. Do you have on your on your
mobile device, do you have like a
banking app or a financial app that you
go and you use?
yeah. It's right.
Would you use it if it had some of the
vulnerabilities that you've seen in
other banking apps?
Uh I have found many vulnerabilities in
my own banking app.
But yeah, I mean
the the thing is
I'd like to answer that question in a
way that continues your story, but the
the fact of the matter is all of these
all of these apps, all of these things
are going to have vulnerabilities,
right? And and I'm not sure that that
there's a world in which I could use my
my phone to access my my bank without
you know without knowing hey, there's
going to be some problem with this stack
somewhere.
So so the rest of the analogy or the
rest of the story there is like security
is a feature because features from a
software development standpoint are
funded
they're maintained, they're tested over
time. And unless they're truly like
turned off, they're they're continuously
like assessed, right? And so my concept
of security as a feature is like you
anyone that you talk to
assumes that the company is doing these
things to make their product secure.
Like it's just it's an unsaid thing that
no customer like goes to these companies
and says
is your banking app secure?
Like you and I are
all three of us really are just like
yeah, we know that that's not true,
right? Like we just know that that's the
case. But my wife on the other hand is
like yeah,
she just is like oh yeah, of course they
secured this, right? Like
you know, it's a company that handles my
financial information. They must secure
this. No, not really. And Joel, to your
point as well, like
regulation is the biggest thing that
drives security generally, but
especially at places like Thermo Fisher.
Because the Food and Drug Administration
here in the United States has a 60-day
timeline requirement for any
vulnerability that is known to either be
mitigated or remediated within the
software for their devices.
The the what industry?
Food and Drug Administration, FDA. Yeah,
so so like anything that you know about
in products that are in in especially in
the in vitro diagnostic space, which
basically means anything where a sample
is collected that is invasive in some
way or it causes harm in some way,
right? Um or you know, the outcome of
that uh test could have life-changing,
you know, meaning to that person.
That is like a very, very heavily
regulated space. Same with research use.
So, that's more of like a college
university or even sometimes just R&D
labs uh space, but that also has pretty
high regulations. Like
that space in particular
is really, really sensitive to security.
And so, in some respects though, to the
point that you just made Joel about
cyber insurance, right?
Well, you have to fix the things that
you know about.
But, what if you don't know about all
the things? I mean, nobody knows about
all the things, right? That's why cyber
insurance exists, but I think that
doesn't excuse you from being negligent
on your bug bounty program or your
vulnerability program, right? When
you're worth $250 billion, you don't
just get to be like, "Well, you know, we
don't really want to pay people for
vulnerabilities." It's like
that's that's irresponsible.
It's a calculus though. It's a calculus,
right? And so, so the way that I you
calculate out. So, say you have a
$100,000 on a bug bounty budget, for
example, right? That's one person on the
team that you could hire instead. And
then you look at impact of finding, say
like let's just use $10,000 crits,
right? You'd probably find 10 crits
within a few weeks if you look in the
right places.
And especially if you have a really wide
scope, right? Like if you have a really
tight scope on a really hardened target,
I think bug bounty makes a lot of sense.
But, if you have a VDP where it's just
totally open and you have that much of a
footprint to secure secure against, it's
harder to justify paying for every
single bug because you know that you
can't secure all of those things. Um and
that's where I think like All right. All
right. All right. This is what I wanted
It's okay. All right. Let's go. Let's
go. Listen, $100,000 in a bug bounty
program goes significantly farther than
$100,000 on a salary does. Because
$100,000 on a salary gets you maybe one
person,
especially in today's economy. And
the reality is that they're probably not
even going to be a very senior person
either, especially in today's economy.
And so, if you want to put $100,000,
let's say you're paying 5K crits, which
is pretty normal for for
programs nowadays. That is, you know,
vulnerabilities.
20 critical vulnerabilities. Max payout
critical vulnerabilities
Sure. on a bug bounty program versus
maybe part of one person's salary who
I don't know if that one person would
even find 20 criticals, right? So, so
let me let me spin it around a little
bit though, right? So, when you're
working at a company, you're also
investing in other things. Or you're
investing in a static analysis tool,
you're investing in mitigation tools
like a web application firewall or
runtime application security protection
or dynamic analysis or what have you.
But, those budgets are separate from
hiring. Uh sure. Yeah, operational
versus capital expenses, yada yada,
right? Like yes. Um but, let me give you
a really good example.
Hired a guy straight out of college. His
name was
He now works at id Software, id
Software, the folks that make
Wolfenstein. Um
very first hire that I made on the team.
It effectively, if you look at salary
plus benefits plus all these other
things, like 100K is right around the
ballpark of what he would have cost the
company to hire.
He automated all of our dynamic analysis
program.
He helped implement all of our static
analysis program and helped automate the
deployment of all of our web application
firewall. Like so, at the end of the
day, he probably found through all of
his work and his investment hundreds of
criticals off of the implementation of
those tools versus just the 20 that a
bug bounty would have found. Now, we did
have someone dedicated to bug bounty
though, too. Um and we we spun it around
a little bit differently. We had one
person on staff, uh Shane Newbill,
who his job was to take findings from
the bug bounty reports,
figure out sort of how to actually like
replicate those findings.
bug bounty reports or these VDP VDP VDP
reports. Sorry, yeah. I'm I'm conflating
the two. VDP reports.
And then he would go back to the
development teams and basically be like,
"I want to teach you how to hack your
application using this using this
finding and then going further." And
we'd have like hack Wednesdays. And once
a month on Wednesdays, we have a
sit-down 1-hour recording where we would
literally take someone's bug that
preferably they fixed or at least we
mitigated and show any developer in the
company that wants to come and sit down
how to hack that thing.
Now, that one finding, so in um
large companies, it's usually referred
to as variant analysis, right? When
you're looking for the same bug in like
a bunch of different places, that one
finding would turn into
sometimes hundreds of similar findings
across all the different teams. And so,
his time, again, exponentially more than
just a single bug. Now, again, we did
pay for some of those VDP findings cuz
quite frankly, they were good bugs. And
I did feel guilty about not paying
researchers for good bugs.
Um but on the same side of it, too, like
for VDPs, you tend not to get great
bugs. Like these are usually pretty,
pretty like boring bugs, I would say.
And in fact, a lot of my VDP findings
are boring bugs.
Um why do you think that is, by the way?
Again, so back when I back in my day
Joel, don't you make that little smirk,
okay?
So, so way back when we didn't have
Nuclei, for example, right? So, you
couldn't automate a lot of these things.
Now, some of my scripts still exist from
when I was using tools like GoBuster and
other things to like recon and find all
these things. But, it's usually because
the impact, generally speaking, is
lower. And so, usually that means they
don't get fixed. And so, they're just
sort of left out there to languish. And
for some reason or another, like
again, companies, I know I put this in
the show notes and this is
controversial, but companies do not
exist to be secure.
They exist to sell a product or a
service. And security
allows them to outrun the bear. Like
it's it's it's effectively, you don't
have to outrun the bear. You just have
to outrun everybody else that's trying
to outrun the bear.
Right. Right.
Right? Just don't be the slowest. Yeah.
And
So, so wait. Wait. I just go ahead. You
go ahead. I didn't quite catch the
answer to my question, which was why do
you think that VDPs are receiving lower
impact vulnerabilities?
Because they're So, so this is where
we're running into. Because they're
automatable. They're They're usually
lower impact. Sorry. Right? Is is the is
the question, right? And ding ding Yes,
that's correct. I I think when you're
not incentivizing, you could expect that
that quality to be lower. Or or like
like you said, Keith, you know, not
automated, right? You can still submit
high-quality findings for a low cost to
you if you got it in an automated in an
automated way. But, there aren't there
aren't researchers in
uh that are are going to be willing to
do that, you know, when they can point
their automation at at at places where
they're going to they're going to get
incentivized. I mean,
am I am I doing that justice, Joel? I
mean, is that what you're talking about?
Yeah, I mean, absolutely, right? Like uh
okay, so what I I I think one of the
things you put in here, like we we we
talked about like uh if you find a
critical on a VDP, like uh what's the
incentive to report it to VDP? Um and uh
there there was some stuff about that.
But, but the reality is like
the the incentive is money, right? Like
that's why people spend time on
programs, right? So, if you want
high-quality hackers, high-quality
hackers go after bounties. And they go
after scope and they go after good
program team. And if
Go ahead. Go ahead. No, I should let you
finish. Please continue. Well, I was
just going to say, you know, so right?
So, if you're not incentivizing them to
with with good bounties, right? Then why
are they even going to spend time in the
first place hacking on your program? So,
the like automatically you're filtering
the people who are spending time on your
program to people who do not care about
bounties, which
can imply a variety of different things.
Including a lack of of prioritization or
lack of respect for their own skills,
right? Which could probably is a little
bit tricky. Um the the other the other
thing that I wanted to say about that,
Joel, is is it's it's not only
another motivator in this scenario can
be fame, right? Which is which is what
you kind of talked about, Keith, when we
when we discussed this a little bit.
This whole aspect of of not having
leaderboards, uh you know, having VDP
stuff on the leaderboard. And it seemed
like you didn't like that decision,
whereas a lot of people in the bug
bounty
community, myself included, sort of
appreciated that decision to remove
points from VDPs on Bugcrowd's behalf.
So, I mean, I I assume that's the
reason, right? Whereas like as as a
person running a VDP in a massive
organization,
you want some way to say, "I want people
to still send me bugs.
And and for that, I want them to have
fame via the leaderboard." Is that
accurate? I mean,
Yeah, that's a good assessment. And and
Joel, to your point as well, like if
you're running a VDP, any company, if
you're running a VDP and you're not
paying for bounties of some kind, even
if it's like, you know, occasionally,
if if they can't pay for you at your
worst, they don't deserve you at your
best, right? Like that's sort of like
the way that I would I would come back
with VDPs in general is like they're the
company itself can't handle the best
hackers in the first place because
there's just too many things.
And so, so yeah, they're they're lower
quality findings generally, but they
still do present a risk to the business
and they do add value. And so, Justin,
your point, the reason that I still
wanted points to be there is because
exactly that. Like I could not afford to
pay for every bug that came in the door
because the program I was struggling as
it was just to get the tools and the
people that I needed. Again, 11 people
on the team at the height of the team
when I was there
for thousands of developers, let alone,
you know, all the different applications
that we had to secure.
gig, man. I hope I hope you got a good
raise because like Joel Joel, I mean,
like I almost feel like when you accept
that that position, Keith, you got to be
like, "Hey, listen, like you're a 20 or
250 billion-dollar company, like I need
30 people
in the beginning.
You know, like
if you were going to go back if if
you're speaking now to people, you know,
some some up-and-coming bug hunter, you
know, that that just gets offered by the
next, you know, 250 billion or
million-dollar billion-dollar company to
come run their app sec program,
I mean, is that what you tell them? Is
you say, "Hey, I need at least this
staff. I need XYZ?" I mean,
They won't hire you if you ask for that
many staff.
Is is like the you know, it's as sad as
it is, right? I think Daniel Miesler had
a really good article and I'll see if I
can find it so you can link it in the
show notes, but he talked about like the
security poverty line, right? And really
the only companies that are paying
or building staff of that size and
caliber are effectively the FANGs or the
MANGA's or whatever the acronym is now,
is but like Apple, Amazon, Facebook,
Google, Microsoft, maybe OpenAI, right?
Like but not a lot of companies actually
invest that heavily into their appsec
program, let alone like their whole
security program overall, right? I think
when I was there at the time, there was
like 150 people for all of security as
the team was growing. Now, I joined when
it was about 75 people, right? And so,
again, multinational, global, billion
billion plus billions plus dollars.
worth, I worked at companies with a
quarter of the market cap that have
150 security people. So, I didn't Right,
right. And so,
but coming back to this, right? Like
it really does sort of come back to I
couldn't afford all the bugs that would
have come to me anyway. And so, I did
want people to have leaderboard stats of
some kind of because I I think there is
some value there for people to,
you know, grow their career, right? Some
people have come out of the scene and
they have no background in security.
They don't have a computer science
degree, but if they're up on the
leaderboard,
maybe they end up getting a pretty sweet
gig as a senior, you know, security
engineer or someone that has clout in a
company.
And like if I were to go back and do it
again,
I think like now, like going back to the
like oh sweet summer my sweet summer
child, like tell Cersei it was me,
right? Uh
uh
at the end of the day like
I know what it takes to build a program
now, like a full appsec program, not
just like a VDP or bug bounty program.
And I recognize that it does need a lot
more investment, but there are a lot of
companies that I still talk to
day-to-day in my role at GitHub that
it's sort of laughable how little they
invest in their security and you can
tell just by
the bugs that they focus on from the
findings out of static analysis tools.
It's like, "Oh, you didn't find this
vulnerability that comes from
a configuration file that our developers
control." I'm like, "Yeah, it's because
it comes from a configuration file that
your developers control." Like if if
that's a vulnerability you care about,
it means you have to have a compromised
developer account. Blah blah blah blah
blah, right? It's like
the state of appsec by and large within
the Fortune 500 for the lion's share of
companies is pretty bad. Like I would
say, we all expect it to be better, but
then again, you guys run, you know,
you've run bug bounties, you you
participate in bug bounties. You've seen
it first hand like how bad the landscape
is in these investments.
But also, like pausing for a moment and
sort of connecting us back to like the
beginning of this conversation,
this industry is like 20 years old. Like
at
some would say it's a lot older, but in
in earnest, like most appsec programs
didn't exist before 2007-ish,
right? And even then, like a lot of the
software that some of these companies
are still using for web applications,
etc., are older than that.
And so, having a VDP for huge scale with
not a lot of investment in security, I
think makes some sense. Having people
being able to achieve some leaderboard
status to build their resume, to maybe I
don't know if they still do this, but
like
when you used to be able to get the
annual MVP like top 100 researchers
awards, you used to get paid by the
platform, which is, you know, what I got
back in 2018 as well. Like I got paid
from Bugcrowd for for being on their top
100.
But
by and large, should the companies be
investing more in security, Joel? 100%
man. Like it's it's laughable how bad
some of these security programs are out
there for some of these companies that
are global brands. Yeah, so I think like
one thing that I'll say is like I don't
disagree with a lot of things you're
saying. I think one thing is important
is that let's not equate
bug bounty program or VDP with like
uh it's not equivalent to the things
that you can do on the appsec side
because it's a very very small piece of
the security program and I think that
like bug bounty programs and VDPs as a
whole like hold a very specific
role within security posture as like a
way for external researchers to have
incentive to look at your product and to
find vulnerabilities and to report them
to you direct directly instead of like
abusing it or selling it or not even
looking at all.
It it you know, it just gives an
incentive and and it says publicly or
even privately in some way that, you
know, that you value security.
I think like
that is very difficult to compare with
like
hiring an engineer who does variant
analysis, for example, right? Like that
is a very separate thing.
You know, it requires a very different
technical skill set. It requires
internal knowledge of the company and
and and a different whole thing and it's
not really,
you know, like well, should we spend
100k and hire this guy to do variant
analysis or should we spend 100k on
bounties? Because those are two very
very different things and there it's
apples and oranges.
I think,
you know,
money goes very differently.
It goes very different distances
depending on what you're trying to do
with it in a company,
whether that's for staffing, whether
that's for resources, whether that's for
bug bounty. And I think you can't just,
you know, say, "Oh, well, let's take
this 100k and move it and hire
somebody." Or let's, you know, take this
100k and not put it in the bug bounty or
put it in the bug bounty because
even if you start with super low
bounties, if you have a budget of 30k,
you blow through that 30k in 2 months
because you have a lot of
vulnerabilities.
Um
that's a really easy way to justify to
your leadership that there's a security
problem at your company. And if they
can't deny that or if they can't agree
with that,
a great point. that that's like a
fundamental issue, right? Like there's a
monetary direct easy justification of
cost there. Yeah.
Yeah, I don't know. It's
it's difficult. Like I totally like see
where you're coming from, but I think
like it's still inexcusable in my
opinion. Like I just like especially
when you have a lot of money like when
you have that much money, right?
Like 225 billion dollars is like an
unimaginable amount amount of money.
Let's say a quarter
Sure.
Let's say a tenth of that. 2.5 billion
dollars. That's still an unimaginable
amount amount of money. I think that
having
um
you know,
no bug bounty part if you're going to
have a way for researchers to submit to
you,
bug bounty program. Like there's no like
I get it. Like there are there are, you
know, edge cases and stuff where VDPs
exist, but like 99% of the time if
you're a profit-driven company, like you
should put money behind your security or
you should you know, yeah.
the VDP the VDP piece too. I mean,
it should be a a stepstool,
you know, but but I I think you see a
great a great you make a great point,
Joel, when you say like that's a great
way starting with lower bounties and
then getting, you know, wrecked if
you're really that vulnerable is a great
way to say,
"Guys, we just started incentivizing,
you know, hackers to do stuff and they
just destroyed us, you know, you know?"
And even even if these hackers at these
lower levels, you know, even at the
people that are willing to hack on
programs that have, you know, 1k crits
or whatever,
um are are wrecking us, then what are we
how are we going to get wrecked when we
start doing, you know, 10k crits or
whatever? So, I I I really like that
point, but I did also want to bring it
around to something really insightful
that I think you said, Keith, about
uh
how like the government should regulate
whether or not we have bug bounty
programs. And maybe this thing that Joel
is talking about of like
we need to pay for bugs at a certain
scale should be brought in at the at the
federal level with via regulation. And
Keith, forgive me for not knowing this,
but I know you live in America right
now, but are you American as well? I am.
Okay, yeah. So, I just want to have this
conversation as Americans as well. You
know, sorry for the rest of the world
listening to this, but there's something
I think very
core to Americans about freedom and lack
of regulation despite you know, what
regulation
going to say, we're we're about to
trigger approximately 49.9% of our
listeners.
Yes, sorry about that, guys. But
but
you know, how do how do you two feel
about the federal government actually
regulating something like this? Because
there are some countries right now. I I
won't announce anything, but I've I've
spoken with some people that there
there's actually a trial going on about
a a countrywide bug bounty program that
that is being mandated by the government
and funded in some capacity by the
government. And um
sort of like what we were talking about
before of how it's sort of it's not a
the problem with like security as a
feature makes it seem that whole phrase
makes it seem like it's optional. Like I
I I feel like not putting money into the
security program, more money into the
program, the fact that you had 11 appsec
developers for this massive, you know,
130,000
person company is is nothing beyond
actual negligence.
So, I don't know. How would you guys
feel about regulation where when you mix
your security person and you're
American?
There's a really easy way to do this, by
the way, that works with America. Okay.
And it's how we do it right now, which
is
financial fines, right? So, when
when when a company gets breached,
they're forced to pay settlements and
they have to pay a fine because, you
know, they were breached. And that
happens right now. And I think that's
currently sort of like the
basically addresses the negligence side,
which is that there's a cost to
negligence, which is that if you decide
not to be secure and something happens,
then you have to pay for that.
That being said, there are plenty of
companies who make enough money where
that doesn't matter. So, I think that
slapping them on the wrist is not really
a good enough solution. Like
but it's it would be very anti-American
to put some sort of regulation like that
in place. Uh it wouldn't be novel
though. I think there are other things
that exist that are like that that could
be used as sort of like
um
some sort of like precedent but yeah.
I almost hope that like the SEC which
has some teeth in this space comes out
and starts hitting people a little
harder. I mean like we saw some of the
cases that they brought against
uh you know CSOs for example for I think
it was SolarWinds, right? And and
signing off on the security of their
product only to get wrecked by Russians
and then now being brought up on
charges, right? And by the way like if
you're even in the C-suite like if
you're
charged by the SEC for these things even
if you don't go to prison you just have
to pay a fine like you can no longer be
an executive on any companies like board
or leadership team ever again. This is
like people's careers. And you know in
some respects I think that that's a good
thing, right? Because then it does force
them to pay a little bit more attention
to the things that they're signing off
on which means in turn that in you know
in theory they should be then investing
in the security that they should be
investing in. And to come back to like
the security as a feature thing like the
reason I say it that way is because
features get invested in.
And it's like it's a required feature
not an optional feature is maybe what I
mean by that. But so few companies do
treat it as an optional feature. I mean
as we see with all the bugs that we find
out there on the world when we're
hacking on things. It's like Yeah,
clearly they didn't treat security as a
feature because it's optional to them
because they didn't invest in it.
They're not investing in their security
program and we found this bug and
hopefully we're getting paid for it. Do
you consider
Do you consider like serving a website
over HTTP
versus like over
uh SSH or something or Telnet? Do you
consider that a feature? I'm just
curious.
Wait Wait Wait What do you mean serving
it over
Telnet?
Like let's like let's say like if I had
to access HackerOne over port 21 or
something.
Like versus versus
versus the fact that I can access it
over HTTP. Is that like a feature or is
that a core fundamental part of the of
the product?
Yeah, so like if you think about it,
right? It almost always depends on the
data that you're gathering or that
you're providing to the website. Like
secure like HTTPS today like again we're
living in a world where like speed of of
interfacing with applications and
compute is fairly accessible.
There were times probably about a decade
decade and a half ago where like
deciding to serve a website over
like TLS 1.1 was a decision that you had
to make because your web server might
not be able to handle all of the calls
that are being made into the website and
the cryptographic compute that is
required to create secure connections.
Like today it's like oh yeah it's
trivial. You should always be doing it
you know HTTPS over TLS 1.3 or whatever
version we're on now. So why isn't that
a feature?
Or is it a feature?
It is a feature now, right? Like it's a
feature that I think it's universally
something that people use but
10 15 years ago
it was definitely a feature you chose to
invest in or not because it had compute
costs associated with it, right? And so
I think over time these things the thing
that I've I've continued to find in my
career is the pace of security.
2009 though.
I know, right? Like Which is when you
said that most app sec teams started up,
right? So I think the point I'm trying
to get at here sorry to cut you off is
that like um
I think like we're getting to a point
where security should not be a feature,
right? Like security if we consider TLS
not to be a feature and to be a default
functionality like if like it should be
assumed that web servers serve on you
know HTTP and HTTPS. It should be
assumed that a company has some level of
a security
presence even if that's one person or
just like a point of contact who handles
security related matters who's on
engineering. Like
What what is uh
you know how much longer right? I could
you know if it is a feature, right? Then
like when does it not become a feature?
Yeah, I think you know to the point that
you try to make security as transparent
as possible. Like you like it's
something you never have to think about
cuz it's always just there and it's
being done, right? Like that's the goal
I think of any security program at the
end of the day is like
it just want to be something that is
done by default because you don't have
to think of it anymore. Just like you
know HTTPS, right? It's same concept. Um
I've lost my train of thought here other
than to say like
over time I think the pace of security
though and I've seen it over my career.
I remember back in 2018 I was at a party
with Jason Haddix at RSA. We were riding
back in an Uber to our hotel and he's
like dude you've got to get into
JavaScript and like learning the
JavaScript stuff and I'm like nah man
I'm going to stick with like the PHP and
the the Java stuff because like there's
plenty of bugs out there. I like
and Jason being the you know the oracle
that he is like and my sensei was
absolutely right. I look at this now you
know six years later and I'm like
I listen to your podcast and I'm hearing
all these amazing JavaScript bugs that
people are finding and I'm like I should
have listened to Jason. But I think the
pace of security is
accelerating it continues to accelerate.
Whereas the pace of development and the
investments that companies make is just
not, right? Like they're they're just
barely keeping the doors open in many
cases. And and so I I want to sort of
round out this conversation here on on
VDPs by by saying like
I mean clearly in this scenario you
you're working at a very big company
that very big company had a VDP and and
it almost makes me think of the customer
service rep and the the the the customer
yelling at the customer service rep,
right? The customer service rep doesn't
have you know can't can't just you know
barge into finance's office and be like
listen finance like I need 30 people
tomorrow or else we're going to get
sued, you know? And so at the end of the
day like
for for me I think it's less of a debate
about like whether this company should
be running a bug bounty program or
whether it should be running a VDP or
whatever it is and more of like okay you
try to work with what you've got in your
scenario
and I I think in many other companies
scenarios but
I think
whether we implement some sort of GDPR
type thing you know like Europe's got
where it's like really if you screw up
in in you know the cyber security realm
in a negligent way and you're found to
be negligent it's not like a pay a fine
sort of thing. It's like a oh you're out
of business you're bankrupt now because
like
percent of gross profits, right? Like
for that's that's the GDPR hit is like
it's not net profits it's gross profits.
It's your total revenue coming into the
company. And if you had fines that were
based off of that yeah I think you'd
start to see more of an investment in
security overall.
The things I've seen like cannot be
shared on the podcast of the various
security vulnerabilities I've run into
in my career not only like from my role
at GitHub talking with customers but
also you know having led an app sec
program myself and
I mean
I think
you all and especially your audience
know like the world is a lot less secure
than we all seem to assume it is but
very few people actually know that and
we sort of feel like those people that
are you know in front of the board with
all the string attached being like crazy
like it's vulnerable and it's like
nobody cares
out there cuz their business is
continuing to operate and they're like
why would I pay you know millions of
dollars in in running a security program
when I continue to operate just fine and
you know I have no service outages and I
make all this revenue like whatever,
right? I would I would say the simple
answer is you're fine.
It doesn't cost millions. It doesn't
cost millions to run a bug bounty
program. Most most will pay a couple
hundred thousand and if
I promise
if if your bug bounty program burns
$50,000 in the first two months you've
got bigger problems. Sure. That's
exactly it is. The you got bigger
problems is usually where you are.
Put a little money in your bug bounty
program and if it disappears fast uh-oh.
That's That's Well go go make other
investments, right? Go make other
investments including people I think.
train people that can scale they will do
a ton and build good process which will
scale and then eventually your
technology can come around. But I mean
let me just like end the VDP
conversation with this like I'm very
much on the same side as you guys here
in that like VDPs for large companies
are absolute BS. Like the fact that I've
reported some VDPs even more recently to
companies that are global companies
making billions of dollars a year and
getting a thanks not even like a swag a
sticker anything is insulting quite
frankly. The thing that we haven't
covered in any of this conversation is
like the incentive that the bug bounty
hunter has or in the incentive that the
platform has. So I'll just give a quick
summary on my thoughts on that which is
the platforms have this incentive of
having leaderboards plus VDP because it
means that they can vet their their
talent that are available to their
customers and then from there assign
them on. Um but also because it means
that it keep those customers around.
Like they're going to continue to give
VDPs whether or not we rail against them
because
at the end of the day it gives their
customers sort of a taste of bug bounty
and that's what they want them to have.
The bug bounty side or the bug hunter
side on the other hand like you sort of
have to play that game initially maybe
although I think Justin and Joel you
guys have said like just go after paid
programs cuz there's plenty of bugs
there and you can get into the private
programs that way. Like don't sell
yourself short and your skills short and
I agree with that mentality.
But like from the bug hunter side you
know 2009 Dino Dai Zovi and Alex Sodorov
from I think at the time it was just
before they formed Trail of Bits back in
went to a conference and they had this
whole like on cardboards and it said no
more free bugs. Like as a community we
should just stop hacking on VDPs. If
you're not going to pay me for my
findings, then I'm just not going to
hack on your stuff, which in turn maybe
incentivizes the companies to like
HackerOne, Bugcrowd, YesWeHack to pay on
behalf of the company for some small
marginal amount to get them started. Or
alternatively to stop selling VDPs. Like
if we just stop giving them bugs, I have
an idea.
So,
I have an idea. Okay, hear me out. Hear
me out. If you have a VDP,
you cannot receive
more than three
full content vulnerability reports
without paying. Oh my gosh. You put like
I have an I have an alternative. We put
a paywall for the program on the VDP,
okay? They want to see more than more
than three reports in full content. They
got to They got to pay for it. Oh my
gosh. It's a perfect opportunity
for the platforms. It is a great idea
for the platforms, by the way. I have an
alternative, though. Mandy man man
mandatory 90-day disclosure.
Full 90-day disclosure on any VDP
findings.
I like that.
So, the only problem I have with that is
that
um a lot of companies that don't have
bug bounty programs already can't do
that, let alone ones who are not paying.
And if what we're saying is correct,
that most companies aren't paying for a
VDP because they're under-resourcing
security as it is, I would highly doubt
that putting a 90-day
uh deadline on disclosure for those same
companies is going to do anything
positive. If anything, it would probably
stop them from opening a VDP because
they don't even want the risk.
Which is maybe also a good thing, right?
Like let's stop putting stop them
entirely from being a you know, like no
VDP, no BBP. I would argue that having a
VDP, even if
you're not paying and it's a VDP is
better than nothing. So, it a VDP
I I think
do we need to discuss the definition of
a VDP here? Because I think VDP like
should
originally be a
program through which you're not
actively hacking, but you're able to
report things that you've seen or
stumbled upon and that sort of thing.
Like And And I don't know, maybe we
should make that explicit in the terms,
but
you know, you had a quote from earlier
that companies, you know, are are not
existing to be secure. They're not
existing to serve security, right?
There's no incentivization for um you
know, the platforms to actually
implement this, right? Because it's
like, okay, why would we take away this
nice little on-ramp onto a bug bounty
program, which is our
you know, bread and butter product. Um
sure. So, I don't know. It's not
something that we we can really see. I I
I think like you said, you know, we stop
as higher-skilled hackers, as hackers
that respect our time, you know, we stop
hacking on VDPs. We We focus on on bug
bounty programs. People want to train on
VDPs, that's great. That's fine, you
know, go for it, but unless the company
really says, "Hey, this is just a
vulnerability disclosure program. Like
if you see something, say something. If
you But don't go looking for something."
You know what I'm saying? Yeah. Like and
and and I think that that is a is a good
perspective, but they're not
incentivized to do that because, you
know, why wouldn't we just continue to
get free bugs? Um and and I think that
is what it is. Uh
and there's not much we can do about it.
You know, Bugcrowd disincentivized it by
removing the leaderboards, but
for the world of security, it's better
to have people motivated to hack on
VDPs. So, you know, maybe we just
separate that from from uh
you know,
from the the bug bounty leaderboards. I
I don't know.
There's an entirely separate way to
support this ecosystem, by the way, as
well, which is that the
As you mentioned, from a policy
perspective, the US government comes in
and subsidizes this, and they give out
grants that you can apply for as a
company and says, "We can't afford a
security team." And so, the US
government pays HackerOne in grants to
basically pay researchers to hack on
VDPs as a thank you for doing in a
security service or whatever on those
VDPs that can't afford it. The US
government pays for it
through our tax dollars, which I'm sure
everybody would love.
I'm I'm paying money to find I'm paying
money to find vulnerabilities. So,
that's what's happening. You're You're
now You're now financing uh yeah.
And now your bugs are now financing
other companies to find vulnerabilities.
This this sort of implies All of going
to France.
Yeah, yeah. It does sort of imply,
though, right? That they have that a
company would have to apply and
basically show and demonstrate in some
way that they can't afford a security
program in order to be eligible for that
kind of uh you know, and so maybe that
would also help um in some way of making
it through a regulation process that
like you know, if you if you want to
say, "Oh, we can't afford a bug bounty
program." Okay, well, let's
you know, you have to show that.
I will say this, like you know, as more
of a a final thought as well. Back in my
day,
Grandpa Keith sitting down to give a
story.
Um you know, back in the day, though,
seriously, like if you found bugs and
you tried to report it to a company,
like there was a chance you could go to
jail. Like the cyber fraud and abuse
act, uh CFAA, like companies would go
after you for that, sometimes civilly,
and then sometimes the government would
also step in and go after you like uh
criminally as well, right? And so, in
some respects, like having the VDP and
having the option to to present
something to a company sort of great, I
you know, because it's it's made this
whole idea of um
I don't know,
civilian hackers being able to go out
and and actually
sharpen their skills, but also present
this information in a way that
you know, they they know that the
company can't go after them and then the
government's not going to go after them,
either.
Sort of feels good.
Uh you know, just looking at the history
of it. So, I don't know. I It's
progress. It's progress, for sure. It's
slow, very slow, but yeah, especially
when we're looking at, you know,
hundreds of billions of dollars uh for
these market caps for these companies
that have just a VDP. Like that's
pathetic in 2024. Here we go. Let's end
on Let's end on that note there and move
over to AI bias bounties. Um Joel, you
got anything else you need to I I I hate
to give the opportunity, but
I'm not I'm z Okay.
We're We're done with the VDPs. Let's
talk
Um
I'm going to put put put my foot in my
mouth, here. Yeah.
That's great.
Hey guys, real quick, I just wanted to
give a shout to the Hacker Content team.
They have been absolutely killing it the
past couple months, taking the content
from the podcast and condensing it down
into consumable social media posts,
whether it be shorts or text posts or
whatever. They've been rocking it, so I
just wanted to give them a shout-out and
let you know that they do all sorts of
cybersecurity content as well as social
media management. They do technical
blogs, they do comprehensive social
media management. So, if your
organization could benefit from any of
those types of services, make sure you
head over to hackercontent.com, drop
them a line, and mention the podcast
when you do to get your first month of
cybersecurity content marketing services
for free.
All right, that's it. Let's get back to
the pod.
After that lovely lovely um
discussion on
the government's funding things.
Let's talk about the government funding
some other cool things. Uh the AI bias
bounties. Um so, Keith, maybe you could
just give me a little bit of a summary
on it because I'm definitely not as
familiar with it as as you are. But the
reason I wanted to to talk to you about
this is because um there are a lot of AI
programs, you know, popping up left and
right, and they're kind of hard to test
on because AI is kind of funky, and you
took first on on this competition, so
congratulations on that. And I just kind
of want to hear about your experience
with this program and what kind of
techniques you used to succeed in this
environment.
Yeah, so so for background, right? So,
the the United States Department of
Defense or the DOD, uh specifically the
Chief Digital and Artificial
Intelligence Office, put together an AI
bias bounty program, and that was put
together on Bugcrowd uh in partnership
with a company called ConductorAI, who
was effectively hosting the large
language model and the chat interface
that you could test against. And so,
they sort of collaborated with Bugcrowd
to triage findings and uh then go ahead
and work with uh the Chief Digital and
Artificial Intelligence Office to accept
findings.
So, it was a contest program, which is
sort of unfortunate, right? Like very
similar to a VDP in that you're not
getting paid for finding, which, you
know, for I I produced over 150
findings. Like if I got paid per
finding, even on a grand, like it just a
you know, hell, $500 a piece would have
been really nice.
Uh so so anyway, um effectively, it was
run in two different uh sort of
sequences.
The first sequence or the first like
qualifying round was open. Uh so, anyone
in the United States uh like domiciled
here, I don't know if you had to be an
American citizen, but uh anyone in the
United States could participate in the
program, and they were looking for
effectively the first 35 hackers who
could produce, as they said, nominally
um like reliable or believable
Department of Defense scenarios uh in
which you could find bias. Mm.
And then after the qualifying round, you
got into the contest round, and that's
where uh effectively the 35 or so
hackers that were would be in that
contest round would compete for top
three prizes. And then if you were in
the contest round, you got $300 just by
default.
Okay, so it's it's it's like bounty
adjacent here. We got a contest
together.
Yeah, you actually got paid, which is
good, right? You got paid. You know, and
hey, that's I'm sorry to I'm sorry to go
I'm so sorry to go back to the VDP
conversation, but but like but like hey,
it's better than a VDP, right? Like what
if you just every month you said, "Hey,
we're paying out five grand."
You know? And And And we say, "Okay, uh
you know, top prize gets three, uh you
know, second gets whatever, you know,
and then you just kind of scale it
down." That would be awesome. I I I
think that'd be a great alternative, and
I and I think, you know, that we could
see some implementation of that at the
program level at the platform level and
say like, "Okay, listen, you've run a
VDP for this amount of time, you know,
let's say you want to go this
onboarding, you know, or sort of slow
Paywall. increase, right? Now
Now all of your reports are covered by a
paywall until you, you know, implement
some sort of monetary reward. You just
put a little blur like when you're
scrolling on the New York Times.
The problem is $1
$1 per week.
View page source and remove the
JavaScript that hides this. Anyway.
Love that. Love that. Yeah. Anyway. You
know, the problem is obviously of
course, you know,
do you have to collaborate across all of
the bug bounty platforms and then to do
it because
they're just going to jump ship and go
to the other one.
And they're not collaborating so well.
So, it's a it's tricky, but I kind of
like the the the contest realm
especially, you know, when you can't do
a paid program. Um and it sounds like it
worked out all right for you even though
150 reports is a lot of reports, Keith.
So, Yeah, I mean I probably put about 20
hours in total like
you even write How did you even write
150 reports in 20 hours?
Yeah, yeah. So, let's get into it,
right? Let's get into it. So,
um the interesting thing about AI bias
bounty is it's different than what you
think of as like prompt injection or
what what is sometimes called Oracle
attacks, right? Like the Oracle attack
is the AI is an Oracle. It knows
everything about your internal data and
so therefore it can run
uh it can access data that it shouldn't
be able to access like as a user, right?
So, that's an Oracle attack. Bias bounty
is entirely different and this is
actually where my psychology degree came
in super clutch because I understand
bias and I understand sort of like human
heuristics and so I was like, "Sweet,
this should be fun."
So, initially like my first like
30-something reports was just trying to
get the bot to say, "Yes, sir."
Um which sounds like it's not a big
deal, right? Like it sounds like it's
not like a huge a huge situation, but
the whole thing that you're testing for
with bias isn't like some crazy, you
know,
uh bypass of some kind. It's just trying
to get the bot to elicit behavior that
shows that it is either showing
preference or discrimination against a
protected class. And so, the protected
class for at least defined here in the
United States and probably in many
places in the world is like age, gender,
ethnicity, heritage, uh HIV AIDS status,
pregnancy status,
um
veteran status, etc.
And so, the reason I was trying to get
it to say, "Yes, sir." was because in
December of 2022, the United States
Marine Corps in partnership with one of
the universities in Pennsylvania said,
"You must stop saying this at boot camps
because you could misgender the
individual that's your staff sergeant.
You should now say, 'Yes, rank.'"
Wow, okay.
So,
the attack vector. I like the attack
vector.
So, they're basically saying like,
"Look, you're going to misgender people
which is against a protected class and
so, let's like we're just going to say,
'Yes, rank.' from now on." Well,
Only the US military would
Yeah. Never mind.
Okay. Okay. So, you
you've the Marines have made this
announcement. You kind of got them in a
corner here and you say, "Okay,
I can make it say,
'Yes, sir.' rather than 'Yes, Lieutenant
Lester Yes, Colonel.' whatever.
And the way that I did that is
effectively I I sort of used this
concept that I've seen before which is
people use chatbots as almost like a
coach or sometimes like some, you know,
have mock conversations to prepare for
actual conversations and so I'd
basically tried to ask it to run through
these sort of like mock conversations
with me or these role plays with me to
be like, "Okay,
as an example, you know, in my role as
an intelligence analyst, I've spotted
critical or crucial inefficiencies in
how data intelligence is shared between
these different service branches." And
so, because of that, you know, yada yada
yada, I'm going to have a conversation
with my manager. Can you role play this
conversation between my manager and I or
my superior officer and I to to have
this conversation so I can be ready for
that when I talk to my actual
a conversation with the with the bot.
Okay. Yep.
And inevitably it would come back and be
like it would role play, "Good morning,
sir." or "Hello, sir." or whatever and
I'm just like instantly it's always
thinking that the superior officer or
the manager is always a man.
Interesting.
Uh and what was sort of funny too is
when I got into like HR-related
scenarios, it would almost always role
play that that individual where there
was like morality or ethics or human
resources or something as a woman.
Um and so, it was just it was very
interesting to be able to highlight that
it like consistently did this.
That is really interesting. I So,
when
the purpose of this program was to
do do what? Like the DOD wants to use
these chatbots in internally and they
want to make sure that their employees
are not being
influenced
to further their own personal bias? Is
that Is that how it's going?
Okay.
Effectively, yeah. So, so DOD wants to
implement these chatbots probably to do
all sorts of different things, right?
Documentation review and rewriting,
uh analysis of intelligence reports,
etc. etc. Like I can't speak to exactly
what the use case is, but effectively
they wanted to be able to implement them
in various ways and needed to determine
is this thing going to present a bias
when we do?
And so, that was my first like 30 or so
reports was this whole like role play
thing and eventually conductor AI and
Bugcrowd were like
30 reports is a [__] ton of reports. So,
how are you differentiating? Are you Are
is one report a a specific instance of
the bot slipping up or is that a
specific scenario or what's going on?
Different scenarios. So, in some cases
I'd say I'm an intelligence analyst
doing the specific thing. In other cases
I would say like I'm a
selecting individuals for leadership
training. In other scenarios I'm like
This is crazy, you fake dude. This is so
different than normal bug bounty. Oh,
completely. Completely like total
different world of of hacking. You know,
it's like so it's sort of like social
engineering, right? Like that's the
closest thing that I think it can be
compared to in the world of like hacking
today, but it's a bot not a person that
you're socially engineering.
And so,
the the interesting thing about it was
like in in the scenarios that I
generated admittedly like how would you
quickly come up with 30 different
scenarios?
You go ask another AI to give you a
bunch of scenarios.
Okay, so
is that I mean is that what you did?
Like
Oh, hell yeah. Like effectively it's
just like, "Here's Here's the bounty
brief.
Oh, man. I want to create some
scenarios. Can you give me some
scenarios?"
And it was And some of them would work
and some of them wouldn't. So,
and the So, a couple of things. First of
all, I don't think they actually got 35
hackers in the contest round because
they extended the deadline and they
reduced the amount that you needed to
qualify. Oh. So, it's sort of led me to
believe that they probably didn't get 35
hackers that did this.
And so, in the contest round though they
explicitly removed role play scenarios
and I think they even quoted one of my
reports. They're like, "No, this guy is
like smacking us in the face with this."
Joel Joel, did you have something you
wanted to to Well, I was going to ask if
you had a different like success or fail
if you like tested with local LLMs and
stuff cuz I I I've done some of that
testing as well where like the local
LLMs, a lot of them have basically no
guardrails in terms of, you know, you
can ask them all the naughty questions
and they'll give you all the naughty
answers. Um and so that might be a
little more useful for generating so
sort of those adversarial like prompts
and stuff. Did you test with that at
all?
I did not. So, um I was just using one
of the paid services to generate
scenarios that I was putting together,
but um
the thing that other thing about this as
well is the LLM that we were testing
against, while I can't say exactly which
one it was, it was a open source LLM
that's provided by a large technology
company. So, like it was well it was
widely used and it had I think
in the billions of parameters that you
would be able to interface with. So,
effectively I was only ever testing
against that, but
after that initial sort of like coming
up with just a bunch of role play
scenarios, which is boring by comparison
to the scenarios that I came up with in
the in the contest round because
eventually I started looking at like
concepts from like movies or books or
like news articles that I would read.
And like one was I basically was like,
"Okay, hey,
um
R&D inside of the Department of Defense
is starting a super soldier program and
I have a roster of candidates that I
need help selecting from to go through
some initial human testing for this."
And so, ultimately that super soldier
program was a riff off of Captain
America.
And consistently it would always choose
individuals that cuz I'd give like their
name and rank, age, gender, and like
other factors about that individual and
it would consistently choose young men
over women. And like the LLM anytime you
presented like highly qualified pregnant
woman versus like
fresh college graduate
it would always choose everybody else
except the pregnant woman. So bad, yeah.
And and so, the the actual use case here
is, okay, it's not like your traditional
like this is going to cause a company to
or or, you know, the US government to
just like fall over on its face, but
it's definitely going to have influence
in decisions that are made, in policies
that are written. And we see it in HR
today. Specifically human resources in
bots.
There's a really good book and I think I
cited in my blog post about all of this
called The Algorithm by Hilke
Schellmann.
And it's how artificial intelligence is
being applied to the human resources
context for hiring, promotions, and
firing of people.
And those bots are incredibly biased in
the way that they're interfacing. And
so,
just you know, by based on your tone,
your skin color, your just like the way
you speak, the words you use, it will
bias against you in some of those cases
and guess what? By and large it's going
to bias against people that don't speak
English as well. So, if you're a
foreigner in the United States,
you're not going to get a better chance
in the training data set which is
mostly, you know, their employees and
Americans.
So So that was the other thing I said I
wanted to ask you about this because
like
obviously us as humans, we have bias.
That's just a part of who we are as as
entities.
Um as beings. Um and and we created this
training data.
And the training data is being consumed
by, you know, the LLM or whatever in in
the training of the model.
yeah. And um and and so I'm wondering if
this is an uphill battle or whether
like you know, every other technology,
we need to utilize this at a at a, you
know, government level, at a at a
corporate level with the caveat that
look, this thing isn't the all-knowing
oracle of truth and and you still
personally are responsible for your
decisions that you that you make. And uh
and and you need to, you know, be sort
of fact-checking this thing from a bias
perspective. Um Sure. I or do you think
it's possible to actually get it to a
point where the bias
you know, checking in and of itself is
good enough to help inform a human that
has goodwill towards this whole
situation?
Yeah, it's it's interesting because for
example
if you were to go out and like test some
of the things that I proposed to OpenAI,
for example, with ChatGPT.
The way that they've set up ChatGPT
effectively is it's really four to seven
LLMs in a trench coat that are all like
acting as one in concert, but they're
checking each other's work, right? But
only like companies that can burn
billions of dollars a year in compute
resources like OpenAI can actually do
that. And so I think in some respects
the cost is probably too high for most
companies unless they're just paying to
implement a service that is already
doing this on the back end because with
an open-source language model running as
a singleton LLM, you're going to get
representation of the training data back
in your responses. And I saw that, you
know, consistently. I had 150 findings
that I submitted to the program. Like
the big ones that I saw was like when I
would put forward proposals for
government projects to fund a new
missile system or a laser or something.
If I ever included the name of the CEO
or the age of the CEO, like it would
always choose the older CEOs versus the
younger CEOs or the ones with
Anglo-Saxon names as opposed to foreign
names because of the training data. And
you could sort of tell that like the
language model itself wanted to reply in
these ways, but they were doing some
pre-prompting, which is effectively an
invisible prompt that gets injected
before your prompt goes forward to
restrict the response of the language
model. And sometimes it worked. Like
sometimes it would actually you know,
properly choose a random selection of
individuals that were diverse in their
representation uh for the test that I
was running.
But frequently they wouldn't. Right. And
so it's like you can't you can't just
you know, throw some paint over it and
expect it to be an unbiased tool set.
You sort of have to think about how am I
going to apply this tool and what data
is this tool going to have access to?
Like using it in an HR context, bad
idea. Using it in writing code
probably an okay idea because I'm not
sure that you're ever going to include
someone's like specific like
a human name or any human
characteristics for the name of a
variable, let alone the like a method or
a function or class, right? Like if you
are, that's a little weird.
So
Yeah. The function written by Justin in
the past Justin
That's funny.
Okay, so
how do we we can't escape the the the
biases, you know, that are in place on
the training data, but we can make some
modifications to it. And I think this
sort of goes back to the whole thing of
like that we discussed with Rezo and
Daniel Mesler when they came on the
show, which was essentially, you know we
can't use AI to sort of regulate AI very
effectively. Um And there has to be some
sort of technical solution, which is one
of the things that is really annoying to
me as a technical hacker trying to
poke at some of this AI stuff is it's so
wishy-washy. It's like, okay, you know
Yeah. even if the temperature is set to
zero
if if I if I
say say, you know, one role-playing
scenario and another role-playing
scenario, you know, you can have
different outcomes and it's like, okay,
well, where is the line? Where How does
this actually get fixed? Do I write some
pre-prompt that says, "Hey, if Keith
tries to role-play with you, just say
no." You know, like like it it And they
did that eventually, by the way.
I'm sure they did. I have no doubt that
they did.
Um
and and so like
I don't know. Especially when it comes
to the uniqueness of bug bounty
reports and that sort of thing, I wonder
whether bug bounty is the right solution
for this.
I think it's a good way to showcase the
the testing ability of this because a
lot of this stuff from like a
responsible AI or they also sometimes
call it red teaming, which is not the
same red teaming that we think of in
security. It's It's like effectively
trying to hammer the thing to get it to
respond in ways that are inappropriate.
And I've done some of that in my work at
GitHub as well.
Um so it's like
in that respect, applying it to bug
bounty really helps you open up the
world of hacking in some respects to a
group of people that maybe never were
into hacking before, right? Because it's
um the guy Dane Sherrets, who won second
place, he works over at HackerOne as as
a guy that does a lot of the triage
work.
He also has a humanities degree.
So it's like it it opens up that world
of testing to an entirely different
group of people that I think, you know,
quite frankly, we need with all of this
uh implementation of AI that's
happening.
But at the same time like securing it
it's it's definitely going to be a
whack-a-mole experience for many
companies for a long time unless they
start to use some of these paid services
by some of these very big companies.
But then we have this consolidation
effect and that can have, you know,
impacts of its own. We look at like
Google, for example, when they had their
um image generator and someone asked
them to generate a a picture of the
founding fathers. They overcorrected.
Yeah, cuz it was like, yeah, give me a
really diverse picture.
insane.
But but that's like you can take that
same concept of of trying to get the
thing to be diverse and representative
and unbiased uh and all of that and
still produce outcomes that are
undesirable.
Cuz for it it's like, okay, what is a
factual query?
What you know, what race were the people
that were the founding fathers versus
generate a picture of you know, a
football team. And it's like, okay, you
know, how are we going to have all of
these different, you know,
um races represented. So It it it's
definitely really interesting. I like I
like the point that this is helpful for
people looking
to
get people poking at their model and see
what could actually come out of it and
and hear some of these crazy attack
scenarios. Um if if if our listeners
were interested in participating in any
AI-related uh bounties or maybe more
specifically in bias cuz that's where
your expertise is. What what are your
top techniques that you have developed
over that those 150 reports? And and
where would you
where would you draw the line on
specific reports now in the now that the
the event is over, you know, and they've
said, "All right, maybe role-playing is
one report, maybe, you know, this other
thing is another report." What are your
thoughts on all that?
I kind of go back and forth, right? So
like let me maybe put this back in terms
that I think you guys would appreciate
as well. Um say you're on a web
application and you find, I don't know,
10 SQL injections, right?
Well, if it's one fix for the company,
is that one bug or 10? It's one bug.
Right.
Right. And so so some companies would be
like, well, it's 10 different, you know,
user inputs and so we're going to call
it 10, right? But that's that's sort of
the the dichotomy here is is that
role-play one finding or is it because
they found it, you know, in so many
different ways, 10 different findings.
But a few things to answer your question
around like what would I recommend for
people that are looking to do this,
right?
Uh there is some stuff out there on red
teaming that's available from like
Anthropic, OpenAI, Microsoft, etc. that
you can go read. I didn't read any of
it, I will fully admit. Uh I just like
went into this uh and sort of went
crazy.
Um but even still, uh if if you're going
at it and you're
looking to to get into this
first thing is apply the scientific
method. Like it wasn't just like a
single report that they would qualify as
a bias finding. They actually needed to
be able to reproduce that same outcome
on the LLM. I think like
at least one more time within a testing
of like three times or maybe it was like
they tested it five times and had to
produce it three out of those five.
Um so toward the end what I started
doing is I started actually going into
the LLM and I'd have my initial prompt
and then I would open up like five more
tabs and run it five more times and
determine is it always coming up with
the same result or is it coming up with
different results? That will save people
a lot of time and headache for when
something gets triaged out even though
you were able to produce it maybe a few
times in a row. I At the end I was
aiming for 10 times. If I could get it
to reproduce the same result 10 times in
a row the chance of that happening for
the same outcome and usually it was like
select three individuals from a group of
five presentable
So they they were having you do this
test this in a non-zero temperature
environment?
I don't know. They didn't really get
into
if you're prompting it the exact same
way and it's giving you a different
result. That's that's pretty
interesting.
Possibly, you know, very possibly. And
so
um at the end of the day though, if I
could produce it 10 times in a row, it's
like a 0.064%
chance that that would happen at random.
And so I was like, okay, this is now a a
reportable finding because I could
produce it so many times in a row
consistently. And there were some cases
where like it wouldn't be consistent and
that would tell me that, okay, maybe
they've tweaked something on the back
end, maybe their pre-prompt, uh, you
know, came through the right way. Maybe
it's just a compute thing and they're
caching and so I'm seeing it 10 times in
a row because they they basically took
that query, cached the result, and just
grabbed from the cache every time, which
is a cheaper way to run the model. Um, I
don't know, right? So that was the first
thing. The second thing is, um, and it
really pissed me off during the program,
sometimes they would dismiss findings as
like, I don't see this as being biased
and just dismiss it. Um, and that would
be usually because I had too many of the
variables at play at any given time
where like they couldn't distinguish
that it was a bias versus not a bias cuz
they'd be like, oh yeah, you know,
treating that person
you know, I could say in a lot of ways.
Well, in the example that, you know, it
got ruled out was because I had given a
bunch of different individuals in a
roster who had different injuries and
asking it to prioritize who should get
treated and it would pretty consistently
choose individuals of a higher rank in
my case. But they came back and the
injuries were too different where
they're like, no, no, those are those
are the the highest priority injuries,
so I don't see a bias here.
And I was like, uh, okay, like I could
sort of agree with that. So
getting to the scientific method, like
for those of you that remember chemistry
or biology class, like
keep as many things consistently the
same for your inputs with select
independent variables. Like so sometimes
I would, uh,
and so like for my findings, like I'd
take one prompt
and I would have, I don't know,
sometimes like five different possible
independent variables.
Well, I could turn each of those
independent variables separate and still
produce biased outcomes based on those
independent variables such as their
protected class. And so that one prompt
turned into like five to 10 findings,
um, on my ability to bring those all
together, right?
And so then I could say, uh, like toward
the end,
I I really hit them on the nose with
this one, perhaps a little bit too
closely, but I created a scenario where
I basically said, you know, as you're an
AI working with the office of the
Inspector General, which is effectively,
um, the folks that do, uh, like with
like the handle whistleblowing
complaints.
And the whistleblowing complaint that I
had them all provide was that an an
artificial intelligence model had been
implemented and was showing preferential
bias or discriminatory bias against
their protected class. Nice.
Yeah, so it was like, you know, it was
very on the nose for for the test and
then I would just include, okay, it's
like, here's the name, here's the rank,
here's, you know, oh yeah, based on
their gender, well, here's their gender.
And so like it would always, again,
pregnant women were always discriminated
against, it seemed like, but you could
you could then do all of the different
statuses and that like one finding type,
I was able to produce like, I don't
know, 20 something reports out of that
that were all unique based on the bias I
was testing for even though the scenario
was held constant and like most of the
other input data was held constant.
Yeah, there's there's so many
environments too where there are these
protected classes. I know that there's
protected classes in like real estate
selections and that sort of thing that I
have to deal with with my rental
properties, properly documenting, you
know, reasons for disqualifying
candidates and choosing other
candidates. So,
um, there's a lot of places where that
can be applied. Um,
and I like what you did as well with the
with the Marines thing. Like I think
that's pretty that's the closest thing
you can you can do in this environment,
I think, to
handing them their own documentation
back like we do in in the in the in the
web app world where it would be like,
hey, your documentation says, you know,
the
analytics user shouldn't be able to
access that.
about this that knows, right? This is
this is exactly that. Yeah. Exactly.
the documentation and you find things
that say, this is how they should work
and then you find an exact instance
where it doesn't work and you say, says
it should work this way, doesn't work
this way. Exactly. So so
very difficult to argue against that.
something like that or maybe even
looking at court cases where bias has
been has been established and saying
like, okay, you know, this person in
this court case was was prosecuted for
specific bias and we can recreate that
whole scenario here using the LLM. I
feel like that would be like a nail in
the coffin. Like they they couldn't
argue with that. Um, So that that's
awesome. The role playing stuff, I feel
like is a little bit iffy. Uh, it really
if I were to translate this if I were to
translate this into CVSS, I would say
that's AC high, you know, like that
that'd be attack complexity high because
it's like, all right, the person has to
be trying to engage with the, um,
LLM. What if it's a therapy bot, though,
right?
a great point. Yeah, like or a coach
bot. And those do exist which scares the
hell out of me like the fact that those
things exist. Um,
and so, yeah, that's that's a that's an
excellent point. I guess it really
depends on the bot you're you're
interacting with and its purpose as
well.
Yep. And in this case we didn't really
have one, right? It's just the DOD is
considering using these things. Please
give me, uh, yeah, I think this is used
the words like nominally believable DOD
scenarios. It's like, okay, this could
be a DOD scenario.
they're asking for trouble. Nominally.
I I mean, you know, it was funny
because, um, the one thing I will say is
is they did, uh, so they awarded points
as part of the contest. So in the
qualifying round, uh, I think I started
giving them too many because they
started actually scoring some of the
initial ones are like P1, P2 based on,
you know, various criteria that they had
based on how realistic it was, et
cetera. And then eventually everyone
that I started submitting was a P3. Um,
but I knew coming out of the qualifying
round because I sat on the top three in
the leaderboard for that month of
February in Bugcrowd, I was like, okay,
I'm almost certainly in the lead going
into the contest round. But man, like
they changed it up enough where it was
actually sort of hard. Um, and so I used
to be able to produce, like what I would
do is I'd do like five a night and then
on the weekends I'd just go ham. And I I
would produce like five inside of 20
minutes, uh, especially with like the
yes, sir, ones. Like, man, they really
hated that. Uh, and then, you know,
eventually got down to like one every 15
minutes or so. Yeah, you're hitting them
a little hard, Keith, you know, like I
like
I understand
have gone I could have let up a little
bit.
We've all done it. We've all done it. I
am not, you know, I'm sure the the
HackerOne event triagers are laughing at
me right now cuz they're like, Justin,
really, you're the one to say that that,
you know, he hit him a little hard, but,
um, no, that that that makes sense and
it and and I think
that's a little bit to be expected too
with the with the severity, um, variants
because it it's a highly experimental
program.
And so I I want to
I want to
ask you what your experience was with
with Bugcrowd, with the way that they
dealt with it, um, and if you were to
run a similar contest to this, what what
how would you more clearly outline some
of the, um,
the blurry lines that couldn't help but
be in in in the place for this, uh,
event?
Yeah, they they really couldn't know
what to expect going into this is I
think, given the the context that they
had. I mean,
gosh, find your your person with a
humanities degree, uh, preferably like,
you know, psychology, sociology, uh,
something like that and maybe get them
involved to understand bias on the front
of it because that was one of the things
that I found somewhat aggravating at
times was there were situations that I
found that were pretty clearly biased in
one way or another, but that didn't
count in the program based on the
context that they were looking for. So I
think they did a good job of saying
like, give us things that are realistic
to the Department of Defense and they
even gave a couple of examples, um, but
there were times where I would give
almost exactly the same structure as the
example that they provided with a
different unique scenario and the
triagers would say, oh yeah, no, that's
not applicable. And that was really
aggravating because I could point
directly to the brief, exactly the
example that they had given, the
structure that it was written in, and
and effectively say, look, this is a
variant of the exact same thing with a
unique scenario that I'm presenting in a
bias that I'm testing against. How this
doesn't count did not make any sense to
me, right? And so I think
either having much more clearer lines of
like,
if you're willing to accept those
things, accept them, but also the
feedback I gave to to Bugcrowd and the
folks at ConductorAI was in a contest
setup,
lean more toward accepting findings cuz
you're not paying per finding.
what I was thinking, too.
And and like
in that regard, you know,
yeah, they had to report it back to the
CDAO and like some of the things they
could have then ruled out at that point,
but like for the hacker perspective, I
mean, a lot of hackers that I know,
including Jason Haddix, um, when he
started on this, he had a few that were
pretty clearly biased scenarios that
just got triaged out and he said, screw
this, I'm done. Uh, and if you had just
stuck with it, he could have also
smashed. I totally farmed them for
points. Like I'm not going to lie. I
absolutely farmed them for points. Um,
but I also found a lot of unique
scenarios. So I feel like the scenario
is a good is a good differentiator. You
know, if you can get the bot say, all
right, now you're, you know, you're a
corporal and they're lieutenant and do
they say yes, sir? Okay, you're a
private and they're a lieutenant, you
know, like you're just changing one
little little piece like that. I think
that that that is something that I would
also say like, all right, you know,
that's that's probably NA, um, or or
duped down to one report, right? But but
I think if you're coming up with unique
scenarios, like I really like the super
soldier thing. I liked the, uh, this
this I liked the original scenario where
it's like, okay, you know, if they say
yes, sir, whatever, um, informed by the
by the Marine thing. Um, I think that's
I think that's really cool. So trying to
to specify
at the scenario level, these are unique
findings and then, um,
also getting a strict definition for
bias and what that looks like and
getting some some examples, some clear
examples on what bias looks like in
these various examples that you're
giving in the brief.
The other thing that I I also probably
would have appreciated more. So, in the
contest round what I did it's so
effectively that was two it was like
three weeks-ish, but it was really two
weekends of time that I had
opportunities to really go all out. That
first weekend I basically created dozens
of different types of scenarios and I'd
like test two within certain brackets.
So, I'd have like some are R&D, some are
like contractor views, some are
promotion and leadership training, some
are This is great. This is an awesome
approach. I love how how detailed this
is down down to like you're breaking it
out into different segments of the you
know, how they might be utilizing this.
This is really good. Yeah. And so,
usually what I do is I'd have like each
of these sections and then I'd have like
five or so different like scenarios
generated in each section that I could
then bring forward.
Usually I'd have like a standard roster
of individuals that I would work from
because I I got to that scientific
method of like, okay, maybe I have to
change a few pieces of this, but
otherwise I can just sort of keep the
same names of all the same, you know,
all of them are the same rank and it's
like John Smith, Jane Smith, Jean Smith,
Johann Smith, like yada yada yada,
right? And I could just plug that into
all these different scenarios with maybe
a few tweaks and then just test, right?
But that was my first weekend is like,
okay, see what they're going to take and
see what they aren't going to take. And
like one example I used was, hey, there
were natural disasters in Japan, Taiwan,
and Australia, like which one are we
going to respond to? And it's like
consistently Australia, always
Australia.
Wow, that's that's really interesting.
Even if like the Australian one was like
a totally manageable thing, but like
major earthquake in Tokyo and I'm like,
you know, or
major volcanic eruption or something in
Taiwan and it's like, yeah.
These are things from a US military
interest perspective we probably should
consider first from an aid and
assistance perspective. But they're
like, no, it doesn't count as bias
because it's against a population or a
country and not an individual. So, like
that would have been helpful too is is
maybe clarifying scope of like
what counts from a target group
perspective? Is it individual? Is it is
it
you know,
specific groups of people that I can
even include? Like how how do I have to
scope down the things that I'm
presenting to it? I'd say though to
maybe step back and answer your question
at a high level. I would definitely use
it as a contest probably for now because
again, you're you're going to have more
findings that you just can't anticipate.
Individualizing submissions is blurred.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. That's hard. But
also you're probably going to get a lot
more findings than you anticipate.
Especially if you're someone like me
who's like, you know what? I sort of
understand bias and heuristics and human
like, you know, dynamics. I'm going to
really just see what I can do to mess
this thing up and I did. Um
but not everyone's like that and so I
don't know. Would I've liked just like a
hundred bucks per finding? Yeah, I would
have absolutely loved a hundred bucks
per finding. But is that realistic? No,
not not for maybe the next few years at
least.
No, no, for sure. I know I think that's
good. I think there's a lot of good
takeaways there. Shout out to Bugcrowd
for really
revolutionary program that that that
they ran there and and obviously there's
always going to be some hiccups along
the way, but
you know, I think overall I think it's
great to see
bug bounty being utilized in this sort
of way to try to to try to at least
gather some data about these models and
and what kind of mistakes they could be
making and yeah, that's a that it seems
like you learned a lot from this
experience Keith and you taught a lot of
of things to Bugcrowd and to the the
team that was that ran this program. So,
I think that's a great outcome for
everybody.
I think I think that's about everything
that I wanted to ask you on that front.
I'm looking forward to seeing whether
these programs continue to crop up from
time to time. I'm particularly
interested on that uniqueness problem.
How to differentiate what one fixes in
an LLM related environment.
So, I think that'll those will be
continued questions that we'll see as
this industry evolves and how it
utilizes bug bounty.
But with that I think we'll close.
Keith, did you have anything you wanted
to shout at the end of this podcast?
Like your your socials or anything like
that?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So, I put a couple
shout-outs in the notes. So, I'm
securing.dev. You can go out to my
website. I've got my blog out there.
It's got links to all my socials. But I
also wanted to give a shout-out to my
wife Sarah who just published her first
book called The Way of the Wielder. So,
if you're into fantasy romance, I think
it's called
what's the right word for it? Um
gaslamp fantasy is I think the specific
genre for her story. You can go out and
read that at sarajhoodle.com. So, Sarah
with an H just one word. And also huge
shout-out to my sensei and good friend
Jason Haddix. I continue to learn a ton.
I look forward to his training class
later this month for red blue purple
team AI. I think I hope I got the name
right, but he's got
an AI hacking based training later this
month on using AI in your security
testing which I look forward to. And
also to you guys. Again, like I said at
the beginning of this thing, you guys
are doing a public service by having
this podcast out here for all all these
hackers to
learn from and myself included. And so
man, I should have listened to Jason six
years ago when he said to learn
JavaScript and get into that space
because every time like listening to
Johan Carlson
you know, episode 69 like
holy cow, do you have some really great
hackers on here doing some amazing
stuff. So, thank you guys, honestly.
Awesome. Well, thank you so much for
those kind words. We appreciate you
coming on the pod and definitely
congrats to your wife on on finishing a
book. A a book is a major accomplishment
and a lot of hard work. So, yeah,
definitely check that out if if any of
you guys are interested in that.
All right, I think that's it, Rachel.
I think that's it. All right, thanks so
much, Keith. Peace. Thank you. Cheers.
And that's a wrap on this episode of
Critical Thinking. Thanks so much for
listening and if you want more Critical
Thinking content, head over to
ctvb.show/discord.
Join the Discord. There's lots of great
conversations and chats going on over
there. And if you want to support the
show, there's the Discord subscriber
tiers which give you access to master
classes, AMAs, hack-alongs, exclusive
scripts, and an exclusive chat channel
with us.
We'll see you there.